<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-28T11:41:07+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sloths Streamentry blog</title><subtitle>Documenting my attempts at building an effective dhamma practice</subtitle><entry><title type="html">MN1 - Mūlapariyāya Sutta - Root of all things</title><link href="/sutta/study/2021/06/23/mn1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MN1 - Mūlapariyāya Sutta - Root of all things" /><published>2021-06-23T07:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-23T07:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/sutta/study/2021/06/23/mn1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/sutta/study/2021/06/23/mn1.html">&lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C5%ABlapariy%C4%81ya_Sutta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/mn/mn.001.than.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.dhammatalks.net/Books11/Bhikkhu_Bodhi-Discourse_on_the_Root_of_Existence.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary-version&quot;&gt;Summary version&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worlding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worlding perceives the 24 “things”, during perceiving the process there is disortion:
The 4 distortions are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is Impermenant to be permanent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dhukka to be a source of happiness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is non-self to be self&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is impure to be pure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then conveives(Maññati) the object, in which [Craving(taṇhā) , Conceit(māna) and Wrong view (diṭṭhi)] cause egocentric perspective to be injected into the experience (in earth, apart from earth, earth to be mine etc). He then delights in earth. This happens because he has not fully understood it. Understanding occurs through the 3 stages of deepening insight. 1. Full understanding of the known through investigating with concentrated mind, the nature of phenomema to determine what they are: “this is form”, “this is feeling”, “this is consciousness”. 2. Full understanding through examination in terms of the 3 characteristics. 3. Full understanding through abandoning. As insight becomes deeper and sharper, one starts to abandon distorted perceptions and views. The worlding then delights in objects, through which he suffers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sekha - from stream enterer up, but not arahant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sekha directly knows earth as earth, because on the 3 insight stages above, he’s progressed, and the distortions don’t occur. He sees the undistorted actual nature, as opposed to the worldings distorted perception. However, the buddha states he should not conceive (injection of I in the 4 ways, i.e in earth, apart from earth), through him still having craving and conceit, and have thought of I and Mine, though these would not build into lasting views (as he’s eradicated those views). This is done in order that he might understand the object. Even though he doesn’t identify with a permanent self among the 5 aggregates, that he hasn’t eradicated ignoranace mean a non-specific floating sense of self can linger and spring up from craving and conceit, i.e “This is mine”. The sekha is then instructed that he should not delight in the object&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The arahant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He directly knows earth as earth and does not conceive the object. This is because he’s “fully understood” the objects. He’s eliminated the root ignorance, and the fetters, craving, conceit have gone also.  Through this process, experience is directly seen without distortion or conceiving and so isn’t viewed as repulsive, attractive, generating lust. He does not delight in the object. He no longer seeks delight in the objects experienced and therefore no condition for a new iteration of samsara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tathagata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is similar to the arahant except he’s “fully understood to the end” the object. Some kind of extended comprehension that goes beyond what is needed to achieve enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependent origin is brought in and shown that the delight generated is the cause of suffering, rebirth, aging, sickness , death&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qE9L5JCE6Tg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-2NJn-qoKcE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fSgJNFcmDQg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cFiWX4SPe4c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jCYJHNOTBOE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ig8BDm7BTYs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-videos&quot;&gt;Notes on videos&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mūla means root - can also be root cause, or the first or beginning
Kūsala Mūla - wholesome roots
Pariyati - The learning of the scriptures / Also means in suttas to a discourse
Pari - means around&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabbdhammamūla pariyāya - Phenomena&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puthujjana - common person / ordinary / (multitude of them, distinct from the noble ones) / wordling&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-puthujjana-the-uninstructed-worlding&quot;&gt;The Puthujjana (the uninstructed worlding)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Puthujjana sees earth as earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perceives earth as earth (with a distortion occuring)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subtle distortion is entering into the perception of earth. Due to deep diflements which infiltrate into the act of perception. Disposition towards a distortion/misconception&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commentary: 4 distortions of perceptions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is Impermenant to be permanent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dhukka to be a source of happiness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is non-self to be self&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is impure to be pure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grasping upon the appearance of the object as concrete and substantial&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having perceived earth as earth, he conceives(Maññati) earth, he conceives in the earth, he conceives from earth, he conceives earth to be mine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misconceives possibly more accurate than conceives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maññati - conceives - distorted thinking, thinking that is influenced by the mental defilements
    From root Man to think.
    Not simple discursive thinking but developed thinking, one that is unwholesole. Building upon the distorted perception to apprehend the object in a mode contrary to its actual nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maññana is the noun i think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Modes of misconceiving / thought influenced by 3 defilements (Āsava? or Kilesa? Āsava are Kilesa, Kilesa is the general broadterm?): Craving , Conceit and Wrong view

- Through Craving - one is inclined/taking to me mine
- Through Conceit - one develops/gives rise to the idea &quot;I am&quot; / &quot;I act&quot;.
- Grasping on I, ego-bias issues around views &quot;this is my self
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of earth with [Craving , Conceit and Wrong view]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Directly conceives earth (conceives to be identical, as self)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locative, he conceives in the earth, as existing in the earth (conceives self to exist within earth (body made of 4 elements))&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ablative case, apart from, seperate from the earth (taking self to be self identity seperate to the material elements)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He conceives earth to be mine (taking the self to possess the form)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He delights in earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After misconceving/miscontruing it (i.e taking to be mine), then the worlding enjoys/takes delight (motivated by craving or conceit) in the earth element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this happen? - Because he has not fully understood it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;apariññāta - not fully known/understood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is meant by fully understanding something?
    - 3 kinds of full understanding: The task in the development of insight
        Vipassana isn’t just being mindful of the present
        Its about insight into the nature of phenomena
            3 stages of deepening insight
                1. Full understanding of the known. One investigates with concentration mind the nature of phenomema to determine what they are: “this is form”, “this is feeling”, “this is consciousness” - Defining the aggregtates, the nanarupa in terms of distinct characteristics (Hardness solidity). What are the conditions for the arising of these aggregates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;            2. Full understanding through examination in terms of the 3 characteristics. After seeing what it is, one perceives them in terms of 3 characteristics.

            3. Full understanding through abandoning. As insight becomes deeper and sharper, one starts to abandon distorted perceptions and views. As they do this they abandon craving and attachment to the conditioned phenomena.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i.e 1. not seeing earth as material form. solidity, 2. not seen earth as non-self, impermanent, non self 3. hasn’t discarded wrong views about the earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then goes through 24 different things (bases of conceiving), x as x… , earth, fire, water, air. beings, gods, devas, 
    4 levels of formless meditive attainments
        - The base infinite space
        - The base of infinite consciousness
        - The base of nothingness
        - The base of neither perception nor non perception&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(These are the ones the initial teachers of the buddha mastered)
,
The seen (visible form, eye consciousness), the heard (ear consciousness), the sensed (the sensed - everything that comes within the range of the other senses, smell, taste, touch) and the cognised (everything thought, conceived, imagined, reflected, ideas, decisions)
, 
Unity/oneness (ekkata?) (states of meditation absorption), diversity/difference (nanata?) (totallity of non meditative experience)
,
all as all (the whole universe of conditioned phenomena),
,
nibbanna
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Kalyāna-Puthujjana - is a virtious worlding engaging in the training/gained some knowledge of the dhamma and is engaged in sincere practice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learner-or-trainee---sekha-say-ka---one-who-has-reached-stream-entry&quot;&gt;Learner or trainee - Sekha (say-ka) - one who has reached stream entry&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Also has a meaning of anyone engaged in the training
    But usually means someone who is a stream-enterer up to Arahant
    [ Bhikkhu engaged in higher training ]

    &quot;directly knows earth as earth&quot;. (abhijānāti - superior knowing (jānāti - to know)), knowing clearly, knowing in depth, knowing accurately, and suggests directness

    Knowing it, in the framework of the 4 noble truths. i.e the 3 characteristics. Knowing the origin. knowing the cessation, knowing the way to its cessation.

    Doesn't mention the perception distortion. (because he has right view?)
    
    &quot;He should not conceive&quot; - (Mā Maññi) (Mā is a prohibition, &quot;should not&quot; like yaa in thai)

    &quot;He should not conceive because he must/should fully understand it&quot;

    pariññeyyam - &quot;shoud fully understand it&quot; - comes from the verb - parijānāti - fully know

    So the Sekha has abhijānāti (direct knowledge), but not yet parijānāti(full complete understanding). The purpose of training is to advance from abhijānāti to parijānāti. 
    To advance the disciple is given the words: Do not misconceive what you are perceiving.

    The disciple in higher training has eradicated &quot;Wrong views of self&quot;. Even the disciple in training still has craving and conceit. So the disciple can still engage in misconceiving in terms of craving and concept - hence, the buddha saying &quot;Do not misconceive&quot; (but isn't about the 3rd - wrong views of self, as he's abandoned this due to attaining stream-entry)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am” arises , we then grasp on it, and reflect “what am i”, then we conclude (“this i am”, “i am that” - referring to the 5 aggregrates) - This is the formulation of a view of self and defined it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even those he’s abandoned the lower 5 fetters, there is still the underlying tendency of “I am”, underlying desire of “I am”, even though he knows it isn’t in the 5 aggregrates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He should not delight in earth” - “because he must/should fully understand it” (pariññeyyam)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;disciple---arahant-asekha&quot;&gt;Disciple - Arahant (asekha)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One who has destroyed the Āsava (deep fundamental dilements: Sensual craving, craving for existance, and ignorance )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He too, like the trainee, directly knows earth as earth, and having directly known earth as earth, he does not conceive earth, he does not conceive in earth, he does not conceive apart from earth, he does not conceive earth to be mine, and he does not delight in earth - why is that? Because he has fully understand it”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t need to say “should not”, because its impossible for the arahant to misconceive the objects of experience (by way of craving, conceit and wrong views) - because he has fully understood it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pariññātam - “it has been fully understand”. With that all ignorance is eliminated, and the defilements rooted in that, fall away too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“free from lust, through the destruction of lust” - fully eliminated, as opposed to it disappearing in Jhana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“free from delusion, through the destruction of delusion”. So he does not delight in the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-buddha&quot;&gt;The Buddha&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He too, like the trainee, directly knows earth as earth, and having directly known earth as earth, he does not conceive earth, he does not conceive in earth, he does not conceive apart from earth, he does not conceive earth to be mine, and he does not delight in earth - why is that? Because he has fully understood it to the end”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”- Because he has understood that delight (nandi) is the root of suffering , and that with being/existance as condition there is birth, and that for whatever has come to be there is aging and death.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bhava - conditioned existance&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="sutta" /><category term="study" /><summary type="html">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C5%ABlapariy%C4%81ya_Sutta</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It begins</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/06/13/it-begins.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It begins" /><published>2021-06-13T09:57:46+01:00</published><updated>2021-06-13T09:57:46+01:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/06/13/it-begins</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/06/13/it-begins.html">&lt;p&gt;The primary intention of this blog is to help me practice by documenting my progress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">The primary intention of this blog is to help me practice by documenting my progress.</summary></entry></feed>